NYSUT Mid-Hudson Regional Office Files. 6174/011
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT Mid-Hudson Regional Office Files
1967-2001
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
6174/011
24 cubic feet
24 linear ft.
Reports, pamphlets, correspondence.
NYSUT's field service operation provided ongoing assistance to local teachers associations throughout the state. The department was divided into several geographic regional offices, and field representatives associated with each office were assigned to school districts within the area. Assistance focused primarily on contract negotiations and grievances, which frequently involved arbitration and close cooperation with the NYSUT Legal Department. These are the files of the NYSUT Mid-Hudson Regional Office, covering the late 1980s through the 1990s. A large section of the files are devoted to Rhinecliff, a Special Act school, one of many created by special acts of the state legislature to provide education for students whose disruptive behaviors required their placement outside the mainstream system. Complicating the different funding mechanisms and regulations for staff under Education Law was the fact that the district was governed by a religious-affiliated agency, Pius XII Family and Children Services. The files document how adversarial the relationship was between the teacher's union, which struggled with issues of salary parity and professional dignity, and the administration, some of whom came not from the public education system but from the state corrections system. No issue -- whether a door had two locks or three -- seemed too trivial to challenge either by the teachers or the administration. By contrast, the files of the Wappingers district, a mainstream public school district, are more typical of the orderly negotiations process encountered by the NYSUT field representatives (later called labor relations specialists) on behalf of teachers, school bus drivers, and other school related personnel.
7164034
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, June 25, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 30, 2013
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Biographical / Historical
Formerly organized under the Division of Field and Legal Services, NYSUT's regional offices continue to provide direct support to teachers and school-related personnel in every local district throughout the state. Field representatives, now called labor relations specialists, are assigned to school districts to provide help with contract negotiation, enforcement of contract provisions through the grievance and arbitration process, and legal representation for members facing disciplinary charges. The Mid-Hudson Regional Office is one of 16 such offices throughout the state.
Scope and Contents
These are the files of the NYSUT field services Mid-Hudson Regional Office, covering the late 1980s through the 1990s. Assigned to regional offices throughout the state, field representatives (later called labor relations specialists) provided assistance to teachers and school-related personnel at school districts such as Rhinecliff, a Special Act school for students with behavioral problems, and mainstream districts like Wappingers, helping with grievances and contract negotiations.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: All other 6174 collections
Teachers' union, New York (State); New York State United Teachers. Archives; New York State United Teachers, Mid-Hudson Regional Office
7164034
- Education Reform History, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Agenda Suggestions, Education Reform Committee, January 3-4, 1990; memo to Regents from Commissioner Sobol re Public School Teaching as a Profession, January 12, 1989; NYSUT information Bulletin, Summary of Recommendations of the Commissioner to the Regents (1/18/89) on Public School Teaching as a Profession; papers presented by Union Leadership Institute and Educational Issues Department, "Local Planning for Union-Management Partnerships in Support of School Restructuring," "Contract Guidelines for Union-Management Partnerships in Support of School Restructuring"; materials re teacher mentor internships
- Teacher Centers, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Question and answer sheet; communication training materials; NYSUT Information Bulletin re Professional Decision Making: Guidelines for Local Leaders; NYS School Boards Association Legislative Bulletin, "Commissioner Submits Recommendations on 'The Professionalization of Teaching"'; "A Region Prepared: A Response by Rochester Area Educators to the Center for Educational Development and the Rochester Urban League Report: A Call to Action," November 1987; memo re the role NYSUT should play in providing services to the teacher centers, April 12, 1988; related memos; NYSUT Policy Background on Teacher Centers
- Copies Used for Education Reform Workshop, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Aug. Rochester City School District Career in Teaching Plan; Joint Statement of Intent Agreement, May 11, 1988; report of the AFT Task Force on the Future of Education, "The Revolution that is Overdue," 1986; memo from State Education Department to local districts, Planning for the Development and Submission of a NYS Mentor Teacher-Internship Competitive Grant, March 14, 1988; The Toledo Plan: Intern, Intervention, Evaluation; Tennessee Plan, November 21, 1981; Mid-Hudson Administrative Training Center presents School Improvement through Effective Schools Research: An Awareness Session, 1987; related materials
- Education Reform History, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Instructor's Manual, Educational Reform: MHRO Summer Leadership Conference, August 19-21, 1987; NYSUT Instructor's Manual for Teacher Center Training Program, February 1988; State Education Department workshop materials for implementing effective schools research
- Restructuring, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  NYSUT handbook, "Tomorrow's Schools," including summary of information re shared decision making and restructuring, fall 1990; related documents
- Restructuring, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Workshop materials
- Ed. Law 3033-Mentor Teacher Programs, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Agenda and related meeting materials
- Ed. Reform Train the Trainer, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Sept. Correspondence
- Shared Decision Making Workshops (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Training materials
- Concordance Decision Making, 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Training materials by district/county; correspondence
- S.D.M. Sample CBA Language (Lell), 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Papers on teacher mentoring and shared decision making
- Restructuring Effects and Opinions, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Papers re accountability and professionalism, redesigning schools, linking restructuring to student achievement; handwritten notes on assessment seminar; list of symposium presenters
- Fran Wolf Mid-Hudson Regional Office Effective Teaching Program, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Facts about the Effective Teaching Program; regional coordinator responsibilities; brochures; letter to Fran Wolf, labor relations specialist at Mid-Hudson Regional Office, re Effective Teaching Program
- CR 100.11, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Summer. Workshop agenda and related materials; text of regulations re shared decision making; handwritten notes
- Articles-Decision Making, 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Workshop materials, including articles from Harvard Business Review
- Education Reform Program-Existence Explanations, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Survey of local leaders on educational reform, with cover letter; teacher evaluation presentation; agenda for workshop, "Practicing Professional Decision-Making"; handwritten notes from workshop; related materials
- Effective Teaching/School Planning Guidelines, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Guidelines for School-Based Planning, 1988-89, City School District, Rochester, NY, presented to the Board of Education, August 29, 1988, edited September 1, 1988; RCSD (Rochester City School District) Mentor Program Evaluation: The Policy Implications, January 1988, for presentation at the annual meeting of the American Association of Colleges for Teachers Education, February 1988; material on effective schools
- School Restructuring Workshop, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Papers and other materials re school restructuring; agenda for workshop for NYSUT staff conducted by AFT Union Leadership Institute, "School-Based Shared Decision Making: Implications for the Union"; newspaper clipping re experience of Rochester Teachers Association
- Professional Development, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  State Education Department directory for New York State Funded Teacher Resource and Computer Training Centers, 1987-88; printed booklet, AFT Educational Research and Dissemination Program; agenda for Effective Schools Consortia Network team building conference; program for Seventh Annual Statewide Conference on Inservice Education, December 6-8, 1987; "rough draft" of paper, "Cooperative Efforts in Teacher Education," by Peter D. Ladd, Ph.D., St. Lawrence University, Canton, NY; report, A Pilot Study of the Impact of Teacher Effectiveness Training, Catskill Regional Teacher Center
- Participatory Leadership: School and Workplace, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Paper, "Education and the Economy: A Diagnostic Review and Implications for the Federal Role," by Dr. Sue Berryman, Teachers College, Columbia University; U.S. Department of Labor newsletter, Labor Relations Today, January-February 1988; bibliography from Teachers College Press; list of materials available through the AFT Center for Restructuring; related brochures
- Task Force, 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Report of the Twentieth Century Fund Task Force on Federal Elementary and Secondary Education Policy, 1983; NYSUT local presidents' survey, with cover letter noting questions on joint decision-making, October 31, 1988; Action for Excellence, by Task Force on Education for Economic Growth, Education Commission of the States, 1983; materials re assertion skills; handwritten notes from education reform staff training, 10/3/88; materials for NYSUT board/management retreat, September 1988; Rochester City School District Career in Teaching Plan: Joint Statement of Intent and Agreement, May 11, 1988; description of NYSUT program to assist school districts on shared decision making, 1988; contract summary by Syracuse Teachers Association re shared decision making
- Mesibov Training, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Dec. Brochure, "Successful Schools Are Student-Centered: Restructuring Education: A program from New York State United Teachers," 1991; participants' feedback form; "How to Set Up a Shared Decision Making Process in Your District"; related training materials
- Education Reform Workshop, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Text of law establishing NYS Mentor Teacher-Internship Program; instructor's outline re Teacher Centers, Mentor-Teacher Internship, and Effective Schools/shared decision making; training materials re brainstorming
- Pittsburgh Education/Shared Decision Making Position Paper, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Newsletter, PFT Point, July 1991; Pittsburgh Teacher Professionalism Project General Goals and Objectives, 1985-86 School Year; position paper, "The Instructional Cabinet and Shared Decision Making," by Richard C. Wallace, Jr., March 4, 1988
- AFT Quest Resource Folder, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Program, AFT QuEST '87: The Challenge in Change: Vision, Leadership and Action, July 30- August 2, 1987; sample contract language, Dutchess County, "Using Collective Bargaining to Respond to Education Reform," May 1987; booklet, AFT Education for Democracy Project: A Statement of Principles: Guidelines for Strengthening the Teaching of Democratic Values; poster for the AFT Learning Line; draft paper, "Finance and Governance Implications of School-Based Decisions," by Henry M. Levin, Stanford University; handwritten notes; articles re effective schools
- AFT Quest Resource Folder, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  AFT QuEST '89 Professional Issues Conference program, "Restructuring Schools: Ideas and Lessons," July 20-23, 1989; case study descriptions; handwritten notes; articles on school restructuring
- NYSUT Staff Guidelines, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  NYSUT Local Leaders' Guide to Research and Educational Services; draft NYSUT Guidelines for Agreements on Professional Decision-Making, June 1989; draft NYSUT report, "The Union Role in Joint Decision-Making: A Legal and Educational Background," June 1989; "Time for Action," report by NYS Task Force on Implementing Educational Reform, November 1989; Report of the NYSUT Task Force on Educational Technology: Suggested Interim Policy Statement, July 1987; NYSUT Information Bulletin, "Educational Technology in NYS Public Schools," June 1987, and results of education reform survey, April 1990; agenda for conference on education reform, September 23-24, 1988
- Stevens Mesibov Perry Program, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  9/25. Agenda; workshop materials re shared decision making and restructuring; handwritten notes
- NY Education Reform-Staff Guidelines, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Nov. Guidelines for Agreements on Professional Decision-Making; the Union Role in Joint Decision-Making: A Legal and Educational Background
- Critical Issues Conference, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Materials on school restructuring for site-based management
- Cataloging Committee, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Filled-in workshop surveys for staff training program
- Ed. Reform Training Committee, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Memos to the Education Reform Training Committee re assertiveness training needs of teachers
- Staff Training Committee, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Staff Guidelines on Professional Decision-Making; 1998 AFT convention resolution re education reform; legal memo to Rochester Teachers Association, analyzing proposed "mentor" teacher and related lead teacher job descriptions in light of Yeshiva decision, February 1, 1989; NYSUT training materials re joint/professional decision-making
- QuEST for Learning Resources for Reform, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Materials by NYC Teacher Centers Consortium; program for 1991 AFT QuEST Conference, "Rebuilding Public Education: America's Foundation for the 21st Century," July 18-21, 1991
- NYSUT Training: Mesibov and Restructuring, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Forum materials
- AFT Restructuring Program, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  AFT Educational Issues Department directory, "Educational Issues Specialists on Restructuring"; handwritten notes; binder contents for restructuring training, including agenda, proposals and plans for restructured schools, resource kit, position paper
- Union Leadership Institute, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Binder contents on advocacy and organizing; participant list; U.S. Department of Education booklet, "America 2000: An Education Strategy"
- Ellenville, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Handwritten notes, legal brief, and other materials re summer curriculum proposal, contract negotiations, and arbitration between Ellenville Teachers Association and Ellenville Central School District
- Agreements, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Agreement between Jefferson-Youngsville Central School District (District No. 1, Board of Education) and Jefferson-Youngsville Central School Faculty Association, Inc., 1989-1992; handwritten tentative agreements
- JYFA-Contract, 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Agreement between Jefferson-Youngsville Central School District (District No. 1, Board of Education) and Jefferson-Youngsville Central School Faculty Association, Inc., 1989-1992; addenda to agreement
- JYFA MOA, 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Memorandum of Agreement between Jefferson-Youngsville Central School District and Jefferson-Youngsville Central School Faculty Association, Inc.; correspondence re salary, early retirement incentive, and other issues
- Financial Misc., 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Spreadsheets re salary steps
- District Proposals (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Jefferson-Youngsville teachers contract management proposals
- JY-CBA, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Agreement between Jefferson-Youngsville Central School District (District No. 1, Board of Education) and Jefferson-Youngsville Central School Faculty Association, Inc., 1992-1994; cover memo, June 10, 1993
- Cairo-Durham Central School District Arbitration, 1985-1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Arbitration opinion and award in the matter of Cairo-Durham Central School District and Cairo-Durham Teachers Association (NYSUT), January 1985; brief re salary grievance; letters between attorneys representing Kingston City School District and a teacher, claiming back pay during military leave, and related correspondence re grievance
- Ellenville Teachers Association-IP, 1982-1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Grievance arbitration opinion and award and related briefs, exhibits, and handwritten notes
- Ulster County BOCES-TATA, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Teaching assistant evaluations for Parisio and others; handwritten notes
- Ulster County BOCES Teaching Assistant Evaluations, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Evaluations; complaint by Gutheil with state Human Rights Division; correspondence between teaching assistant and Ulster County BOCES re probation and termination
- Ulster County BOCES-TATA, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  List of evaluation summaries for teaching assistants; character reference letters for Angelina Parisio; handwritten notes
- UBO I.P., 1991 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Details of charges against the district re termination of teaching assistants for union organizing; related documentation
- Dec. E-H, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Handwritten notes re Improper Practice charge; letter to superintendent of schools for Ulster County BOCES from Ulster BOCES Teacher Organization, requesting recognition of aides and teacher assistants, May 17, 1990
- UBO PERB, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Teaching assistant/aide evaluations; handwritten notes for PERB hearing; correspondence
- UBO PERB, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  PERB brief in the matter of Ulster County BOCES Teacher Assistants and Aides, Chapter of Ulster County BOCES Teacher Organization, charging party, and Ulster County Board of Cooperative Educational Services, respondent; handwritten notes; handwritten letter re missing files; related materials
- AFT Guide to Political Power, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Document re establishing a COPE Committee (Committee on Political Education)
- Union Representative's Training Manual, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  NYSUT/AFT union representative instructor's manual
- AFT Assign-Houston, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  Handwritten notes; anti-NEA brochure for school-related personnel
- H.T.A. ODDM Johnson City Model, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  Workshop materials, "Nurturing Individual Responsibility through Reality Therapy and Control Theory"
- GFA Workshop, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  10/6. Grievance form; Collective Agreement between the Greenville Central School District and the Greenville Faculty Association, July 1, 1987-June 30, 1990; workshop materials re collective bargaining; memo re seminar, with topic outline
- Greenville Exec. Effective Planning, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  Workshop materials re group dynamics, planning
- Carnegie Report, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Report of the Task Force on Teaching as a Profession of the Carnegie Forum on Education and the Economy, "A Nation Prepared: Teachers for the 21st Century," May 1986
- HF Negotiation Workshop, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Tentative agenda; workshop materials; handwritten notes
- Union Leadership Institute-Leadership Development Coordinator Conference, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  AFT research reports re salary trends; related training materials
- SRP Seminar, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  List of participants; "Developing a Relationship between the Union Representative and the School Administrator," "Contract Enforcement," and related training materials
- SRP Negotiations, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Training materials re bargaining process
- Summer Leadership Conference, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Materials re shared decision making, restructuring
- SRP Conference-Union Representative I, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Conference evaluations (verbatim replies); materials re contract enforcement and related topics
- School Budget Elections, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  NYSUT document, "Political Action at the Local Level"; campaign brochures and flyers re budget vote, school board elections
- School Funding, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  NYSUT document, "An Introduction to School Finances," prepared for Summer Leadership Conference; form and instructions for State Education Department annual financial report for school districts
- Wallkill Staff Development Day Reform Program, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  Brochure; newsletter; final draft, "Fund for Innovation," January 1990; draft papers re restructuring, shared decision making; handwritten notes
- OSHA Training, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  Agenda; materials on health and safety laws; guide to hazardous substances for school science laboratories; air quality fact sheet; handwritten notes
- SRP Negotiations Workshop, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  Salary comparisons; local newsletters; fact sheet re Taylor Law; materials re dynamics of bargaining; contract analysis checklist for school-related personnel
- Unit XXIII Folders 1-10 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  Role-play exercises, with descriptions of parliamentary procedure
- How to Run a Union Meeting, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  AFL-CIO booklet, "How to Run a Union Meeting"; role-play exercises
- WFW-Activity Drivers Unit Work, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 1)